Guide to the Henchman S. Soule Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henchman S. Soule papers
1839-1859
MS 1110
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
Correspondence, account books, business papers, and ships' records, relating to the many commercial concerns and shipping ventures Henchman S. Soule and his brothers conducted from New Haven, Connecticut, including world voyages and investments in California gold exploration.
Soule, Henchman Sylvester, 1799-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Harvard School of Business Administration May, 1942.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Henchman S. Soule of New Haven, Connecticut held an extensive shipping business. Ships of which he was a part owner with his brothers, or of which he was agent, traded with many foreign countries, as well as with ports in the United States. Two of his brothers and a nephew were masters of many of the ships. He had many private investments, and was agent for two commercial concerns, the papers of which are with the collection. The California Gold Expedition was one of his ventures.
Henchman S. Soule died in 1859. His papers were given to Yale University Library by the Harvard School of Business Administration in May 1942.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, account books, business papers, and ships' records, relating to the many commercial concerns and shipping ventures Henchman S. Soule and his brothers conducted from New Haven, Connecticut, including world voyages and investments in California gold exploration.
Budgets, Personal; Business; Shipping; Ships -- Cargo; Voyages around the world; California -- Gold discoveries; New Haven (Conn.) -- Commerce; Ships' papers; Businessmen; Soule, Henchman Sylvester, 1799-
- Correspondence
  - Personal, 1842-1858 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business, 1844-1859 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
- Business papers
  - Account books with Merchants Bank, 1839-1855 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bank communications from Merchants Bank, 1846-1852 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Accounts current, 1845-1857 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Household account book, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous account book, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal bills, 1846-1852 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Freight bills, 1853-1857 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Investments, 1847-1859 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Invoices, bills, receipts, 1845-1859 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notes, 1841-1857 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - California Expedition, 1849-1852 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fowler & Co., 1856-1858 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rippowam Co., 1855-1858 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous agreements, 1844-1857 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous shipping papers, 1848-1858 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Printed matter, 1851-1852 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Ships' papers [includes accounts, bills, receipts, notes, disbursements, insurance policies, letters, and lists of cargoes, passengers, provisions, and charter parties]
  - Ship Arthur, 1848-1855 (Box 2)
  - Bark Corporal Trim, 1854 (Box 2)
  - Brig George Loyall, 1844-1846 (Box 2)
  - Bark Glen, 1847-1854 (Box 2)
  - Ship Haidee, 1844-1852 (Box 2)
  - Ship Harraseeket, 1856-1859 (Box 2)
  - Ship Lydia, 1850-1854 (Box 2)
  - Bark Madonna, 1849-1852 (Box 2)
  - Ship Milwaukee, 1853-1858 (Box 2)
  - [Brig Norman?] [possibly Brig Rush], 1851-1852 (Box 2)
  - [Bark Prague?], 1851-1852 (Box 2)
  - Brig Rush, 1849-1853 (Box 3)
  - Ship Sentinel, 1855-1857 (Box 3)
  - Ship Souter Johnny, 1850-1859 (Box 3)
  - Ship Superior, 1855-1858 (Box 3)
  - Ship Tam O'Shanter, 1850-1854 (Box 4)
  - Ship Uncle Toby, 1852-1859 (Box 4)
  - Ship Yorick, 1856-1859 (Box 4)
- Account book, 1849-1857 (Box 5)